<chapter>
<title>Arthur and The Justian Plague
<indexterm><primary>Epidemic</primary><secondary>Bubonic Plague</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Bubonic Plague</primary></indexterm>
</title>
<para>
The cold period lasted 9 years in the tree ring records.
This event left an impact in both the recorded history around the world and the climate proxies allowing for a reconstruction of what a global winter is like.
</para>
<para>
The cloud cover started on March 24, 535 and ended on June 24, 536.
It's ocular density was 2 and a half times the explosion of Tambora (1815).
</para>
<para>
'There was a sign from the sun, the like of which had not been reported before. The sun became dark and its darkness lasted for 18 months.  Each day, it shone for about four hours, and still this light was only a feeble shadow.  Everyone declared that sun would never recover its full light again.'
</para>
<section>
<title>516 AD: Badon Hill
</title>
<url>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Badon</url>
<para>
This battle was between the Britons and the Anglo-Saxons in Britain.
There is controversy over the date of this battle as the Anneals Cambriae had an unreliable dating of Easter before 525.
Consider though that such a battle probably would have taken place late summer or early fall when it became obvious that crop failure was dooming even the eldest children of the group.
</para>
<para>
Given Rabul's location on the globe, a Global 'Winter' would have resulted.
So imagine that the first couple of years when famine was present, the Anglo-Saxons raided some areas of Britain for supplies.
The couple of reasonable years would have eased the need for such raids but not let them be forgotten.
When the cold weather returned in the fourth years, the raids resumed.
The fifth year, the whole Anglo-Saxon presence would have been looking to find anyway to ease the famine and the Britons would not be welcoming.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>535 AD - 536 AD: 535, Mar 24- 536, Jun 24 AD -  Year of Darkness
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>535 AD - 544 AD: Year of Darkness - global winter
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>535 AD - 595 AD: Year of Darkness - total weather affect
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>537 AD: Death of Arthur
<indexterm><primary>Arthur</primary></indexterm>
</title>
<para>
In the Anneals Cambriae entry for 537 states 'The Strife of Camlann in which Arthur and Medraut fell [and there was death in Britain and in Ireland].'
The '[and there was death in Britain and Ireland]' ties the death of Arthur to the deaths resulting from the 535 event.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>535 AD: Failure of Bread<citation>AnnalesUlster</citation>
<indexterm><primary>Famine</primary><secondary>Failure of Bread</secondary></indexterm>
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>539 AD: Failure of Bread<citation>AnnalesUlster</citation>
<indexterm><primary>Arthur</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Famine</primary><secondary>Failure of Bread</secondary></indexterm>
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>540 AD: Failure of Bread<citation>AnnalesUlster</citation>
<indexterm><primary>Arthur</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Famine</primary><secondary>Failure of Bread</secondary></indexterm>
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>541 AD - Justian Plague.  Second Occurrence of Plague in Europe
<indexterm><primary>Historical</primary><secondary>Justian Plague</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Epidemic</primary><secondary>Bubonic Plague</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Bubonic Plague</primary><secondary>Justian Plague</secondary></indexterm>
</title>
<para>
An Empire is not only the ground help by those disposed to its existence, but also the people.
Its citizens who serve as government, religious, cultural and business leaders from ties between communities that are based on trust and mutual understanding.  When plague strikes, the indiscriminate manner of death leads to an uneven distribution of contacts over the larger state.
</para>
<para>
With such a reduction in communal contentedness, the concept of greater nationhood ceases to exist.
The trust and mutual understanding coming from known personal constants reduces to knowledge of a brother's cousin's friend's cousin.
Family to Family contacts exist if the Family exists.
After a plague, a family's reduction in size reduces it knowledge of the business and its properties.
</para>
<para>
The Manorialism started in the Third century contributed to this reduction in knowledge because instead of masters of a craft spread out amount the population, they were isolated in number to a Manor.
The lost of an estates master with the job following to a journeyman would cause the Estate owner to seek out a master of the craft if they could be found.
</para>
<region>Global</region>
<event_type>Epidemic</event_type>
<section>
<title>541 AD: Justian Plague.  Second Occurrence of Plague in Europe
</section>
</section>
</chapter>
