<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//Holocene-Team//DTD DocBook V4.2-Based Variant V1.0//EN" "file:///home/codynivens/holocene_book/DTD/holocene-doc">

<book id="Climate and History"
	xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">
<title>Climate and History</title>

<bookinfo>
	<authorgroup>
	<author>&person.codynivens;</author>
	</authorgroup>
	<pubdate><?latex \today ?></pubdate>
        <xi:include href="revisions.xml"/>
</bookinfo>

<?latex \setcounter{page}{5} ?>

<part>
	<title>Preface</title>
	<xi:include href="holocene-attributions.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="preface.xml"/>
</part>

<?latex \cleardoublepage ?>

<!-- Contents -->
<toc/>
<?latex \cleardoublepage ?>

<part>
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<xi:include href="introduction.xml"/>

</part>

<part>
	<title>Climatology</title>

<partintro>
	<title>Climatology</title>
<para>
Climatology is the study of Climate, scientifically defined as weather conditions averaged over a period of time.  
What creates weather and how it affects civilization is of interest to society as weather affects food supplies and economic growth.  
Climatology differs from meteorology in that Meteorology is concerned with sort term forecasts for the week, the season and the year.  
Climatology is concerned with how weather has changed over centuries and millennia.
</para>
<para>
There are three major factors affecting climate.  First, the major factor is the oceans as their currents and patterns influence the majority of the Earth.  Second, solar affects the atmosphere via solar heating.  Heat creates thermal updrafts which affect the circulation of the air.
</para>
<para>
The third factor affecting the climate are events which can not be predicted, yet have a global impact.
These events are volcanoes and meteor impacts.  If a volcanic eruption is large enough, it can directly affect the weather by sulfuric acid cooling the atmosphere as well as the cooling effect of the shadowing of the oceans by the ash cloud created by the eruption.  
Eruptions which are spaced close together can have an accumulative affect.  
These events can create a Global Winter which affecting all parts of the world.
</para>
<para>
This section discuses the ocean circulation patterns and how they affect various regions of the world.  
Catastrophic events are then covered by examining volcanic eruptions and impacts.  
Then a definition of Global Winter is formed as well as a discussion of what such a winter entails.
</para>
</partintro>
	<xi:include href="ocean.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="climate_reconstruction.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="climate_factors.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="global_winter.xml"/>
</part>

<part>
	<title>History by Climate Change</title>
<partintro>
</partintro>

<chapter id="history_by_climate">
<title>History by Climate</title>
        <xi:include href="genesis.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="first_plague.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="crisis_3rd_century.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="arthur.xml"/>
</chapter>


</part>

<!--
 <part>
	<title>Time Line</title>
		
	<xi:include href="timeline.xml"/>
</part>
-->

<part>
	<title>Bond Event 0</title>
	<xi:include href="bond_zero.xml"/>
</part>

<lot/>
<part>
	<title>Appendices</title>

	<xi:include href="appendices.xml"/>

</part>

<bibliography>
	<title>Bibliography</title>

	<xi:include href="bibliobooks.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="biblioweb.xml"/>

</bibliography>



<part>
<title>Glossary</title>
<xi:include href="glossary.xml"/>
</part>

<part>
<title>Index</title>
<index/>
</part>


</book>
