<chapter>
<title>Bronze Age Collapse
</title>
<para>A great question in history has always been the collapse of the Prototypical Manoral societies in the Macadonian and Greek areas.  With an event which produced an 18 year substandard harvest resulting in a transgenerational famine
 with peoples facing genocide due to the weather.   Peoples searching for substance flooded south into any area that had any food without care as to those there already.  The most famous is the
Sea People.
</para><para>
The appearance of the Sea People it is believed were peoples from the various islands of the Mediterranean.  It is speculated that the Trojans and their allies were a major part of the Sea People.</para>
<section>
<title>2200 BC - 2100 BC: 4.2 Kiloyear Event</title>
<para>A 180-km-long wall, the 'Repeller of the Amorites', was built across central Mesopotamia to stem nomadic incursions to the south.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>2200 BC - 1900 BC: Bond 3 - 4.2 Kiloyear Event
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>2000 BC - 1700 BC: The Lycian Sea People
<indexterm><primary>Sea People</primary></indexterm>
</title>
<event_type>Cultural</event_type>
</section>
<section>
<title>1399 BC - 1300 BC: The Sherden Sea People
<indexterm><primary>Sea People</primary></indexterm>
</title>
<event_type>Cultural</event_type>
</section>
<section>
<title>1150 BC: Trojan War
</title>
<para>That the Trojan war is placed in the bronze Age Collapse, the question of motives is that the Trojans and their allies may have been the
Sea Peoples and were finally cornered as told by the Iliad.
</para><para>
Apollo his association with mice and their caring of plague was noted in the Iliad.  That such an association should be stated so clearly indicated along standing understanding of causes of disease.
</para><para></para>
<event_type>Cultural</event_type>
</section>
<section>
<title>1206 BC - 1150 BC: Bronze Age Collapse
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1200 BC - 1190 BC: Mycenea 
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1159 BC: Helka 3, Iceland VEI 6
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1159 BC - 1141 BC: Downturn of environment: Tree Ring Event
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1200 BC - 1100 BC: Late Bronze Age Collapse
</title>
<region>Global</region>
<event_type>Climatic</event_type>
</section>
<section>
<title>1225 BC - 1175 BC: Poseidon's Horses: Earthquake Swarm
<indexterm><primary>Earthquake</primary><secondary>1225 BC - 1175 BC: Posedion's Horses</secondary></indexterm>
</title>
<region>Near East</region>
<event_type>Earth</event_type>
</section>
<section>
<title>1100 BC - 800 BC: Greek Dark Ages
</title>
<event_type>Cultural</event_type>
</section>
</chapter>
