<chapter>
<title>Genesis
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Genesis</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<partition>History by Climate</partition>
<para>My maternal grandmother corralled my one day just before I went off to college.  She exponded to me the history of the Bible and that someday I 
or someone else would demonstrate it's validity.
</para>
<para>In the years since, I have watched the fate of archeology as one school and then another demonstrated why or why not biblical events could occur.
</para>
<section>
<title>10900 BC - 9600 BC - Day 1 Let there be Light
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Day 1</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>
One of the things that fascinated me about the Tunguska
 blast was the report of the bright sky at night in London allowed reading the newspaper.
An effect after the event that lasted 9 days.
This luminous effects is a result of ice crystals in the atmosphere and it is believed that it was similar to the display caused by the reentry of the space shuttle.
A similar effect on an significantly larger scale would have occurred at the Clovis impact.
</para>
<para>
God spoke (the noise of the impact), and there was Light (the luminescent display by ice particles over the northern hemisphere).
</para>
<para>
Simplistic explanation?
Perhaps, but consider that Mankind at that time was dispersed over a large area of the globe.
Such an event  would be known by by those in the Eurasian continent with awe as a supernatural event.
Unlike the peoples of the new world for which the event was catastrophe, the Old world was awed into the beginnings of awareness of a single Creator of events.
</para>
<section>
<title>10900 BC - 9600 BC: Day 1 Let there be Light
</title>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>9600 BC - 9100 BC - Day 2 - Dividing the Waters
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Day 2</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>
The end of the Younger Dryas started the thawing of the ice across the contents of world.
This would especially affect anyone living on the plains around the Exiune Sea (ancient Black Sea).
Molins would release random amounts of water at random times of the warm season (summer).  Such conditions are not conducive to any activities.
Hunting be based on following herds as they transverse the tundra below the ice fields as the retreat north.
</para>
<para>
During such a period of sudden flooding, the question of where is the normal flow of water coming from would be a primary need.
Rivers would swell with sudden influxes of water and streams that seem to have a permanence would disappear as the ice moves north.
By the end of the period most major rivers had formed.
Their wandering over their ancient beds would continue, but their jumping over vast areas would have subsided.
</para>
<section>
<title>9600 BC - 9100 BC: Day 2 - Dividing the Waters
</title>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>9100 BC - 8300 BC - Day 3: Dry Land
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Day 3</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>
During the thawing of the great ice sheets over the Eurasian continent, flooding was a constant feature along a wide area.
Any area below an ice field would have been subject to flash floods when a mulon opens from a surface lake on the ice.
</para>
<para>
This constant flooding made life difficult for more than just man.
Plants and nesting animals would have little change of survival in such floods.
Humans adapted by either retreating to the hills above such flood areas or fortified their towns with stone towers to act as a water break allowing the flood waters to go around a town.
Jericho had such a stone tower giving the community the shape of a foot.
I believe that part of the ancient traditions in Judaism which refer to worship of the 'foot' refer to similar structures that acquired a purely religious function when the flooding finally subsided.
</para>
<para>
This Day's end effect was the creation of the herbs, grasses and fruit trees.
Plants could finally establish permanent residence on the plains and mankind began planting grains.
</para>
<section>
<title>9100 BC - 8300 BC: Day 3: Dry Land
</title>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>7400 BC - Day 4 - Sun, Moon and Stars 'Lights in the Firmament'
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Day 4</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>
A 'Day' which seems to reflect the growing wonder at God's creation.
A cold period with low atmospheric particulates or moisture.
Cold nights offer clearer sighs of the stars, planets and possible Aurora Brollies displays.
</para>
<section>
<title>7400 BC: Day 4 - Sun, Moon and Stars 'Lights in the Firmament'
</title>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>6100 BC - Day 5 - Water and Air creatures
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Day 5</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>
After such flooding caused by the ice melt, the rivers and streams would have been washed clean.
The time needed for fish to establish themselves in the rivers and streams would have varied by species.
I think that as fish populations increase, so would Avian species preying on them.
</para>
<section>
<title>6100 BC: Day 5 - Water and Air creatures
</title>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>6000 BC - 5700 BC - Day 6 - Land creatures and Man
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Day 6</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>
I would contend that Days 5 and 6 are a bit 'shorter' that the previous one.
These reason for the is that as the Lord 'rested' and man played in the Garden of Eden, the ocean level rose.
Eventually, they cased the inflow of sea water into the Black Sea.
</para>
<para>
The domestication of animals has allowed man to expand in a manner never before seen in human history. While some animals have been with mankind for millennium, others are more recent and some will never be tamed.
As man's awareness has grown over time, the dependency on livestock for food and labor has grown as well.
</para>
<section>
<title>6000 BC - 5700 BC: Day 6 - Land creatures and Man
</title>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>5700 BC - Day 7 - The Lord Rested
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Day 7</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<section>
<title>5700 BC: Day 7 - The Lord Rested
</title>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>5677 BC - God Comes to visit
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>God comes to visit</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>
What would a person consider as a visit from God?  I content that a volcano exploding with enough force would generate a sound heard around the world.
</para>
<para>
I could also contend that an impact event would also qualify.  First the bright sreak across the sky.  Then an explosion generating a massive sound. 
Two such impacts are the Tunguska event and the Chelyabinsk meteor.
</para>
<section>
<title>5677 BC: God Comes to visit
</title>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>5500 BC - Cast out of Eden - Flooding of the Black Sea
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Cast out of Eden</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>
At that time the Black sea area was truly Eden.
Large fresh water lake with gentle rolling hills.
Four rivers flowing to the area proving a guide out of the area.
Having had several thousand years to adapt to the valley, it's loss would be a religious experience.
The Black Sea basin before the flooding by the sea was a paradice compaired to other areas during the Holocene. Fresh water with four river running into it profiding trails leading out. The plain would have been firtile with grass as well as marshes with birds, fish and other animals. 
</para>
<para>
Depending on the rate of rise of the wasters, one could find oneself at the edge of the new ocean with literally the cloths on ones back.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Eve's Apple
</title>
<para>
One of the quesions that has always interested me is the question of Eve, the apple and the snake.  Apple trees are an awesome source of food.
It can be dried.  I can imagine some women trying to harvest apples and running into snakes in the trees.  Not a desirable work condition.
I imagine that to remady this, they cut branches to skirt the tree pointing downward so that a snake would fall back to earth trying to climb the tree.
Now imagine some of the branches are apple and being stuck into the apple tree, they grew.
Not somethings that those who grow beards and know things know about.
</para>
<section>
<title>5500 BC: Cast out of Eden - Flooding of the Black Sea
</title>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>3250 BC - Noah's Flood
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Noah's Flood</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>
When research conducted by William Ryan, Walter Pitman was first published in 1998, the Christian community was not very receiving.
First, the Biblical flood covered the whole world, while the flooding of the Black Sea basin was not global in nature.
</para>
<para>
Research done by Abbott, et la concerning specific types of chevron dunes along the coasts of various places lead to the discovery of the Buckle Crater.
This event would have been global with solid rain for several months.
</para>
<para>
This event is called the Piora Oscillation and lasted from 3250BC to 2900BC.
A Greenland GISP2 ice core sample shows a sulfate spike and methane trough about 3250 BC.
</para>
<section>
<title>3250 BC: Deucalion Deluge
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>3250 BC: Noah's Flood
</title>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>1628 BC - Destrection of Sodom and Gomorrah
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Destruction of Sodom and Gomorrah</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>Thera had two minor eruptions before exploding.  The first eruption cast a plume trace to the northeast of the 
Mediteranian.  Traces of the plume have been found in Turkey and parts of Lebinon.  The second eruption was towards the
south east over the land of Isreal.  Abraham  in the plains of Mamre would have seen the first eruption as something 
devine and safe as no fallout from the plume reached his location.  The interviening months between the first and second
eruptions would have allowed time for new of the destruction caused by the fallout of the first explosion to filter to 
Abraham.
</para>
<para>When the second explosion occured and the plume came overhead, Abraham was visited by people who survived the first plume.
These survivors were surely angles have survived by being on God's side.  They sought to warm Lot, his family and friends
that the fallout from the plume could destroy them.  Who or what the angles sent to Lot in Sodom is unknowable.
There effect on the crowd at Sodom seems real enough.  If something or someone is brought to the city with knowledge
of what is happening with the eruption plume overhead would be very sought after.  
</para>
<para>
Steven Collins' work at Tall el-Hammam in Jordon has shown that the city he found matches the description of Sodom
as defined in the Bible.  During the work of excuvation, large quantities of glass where found that resemble Trinitite
indicating a very hot explotion.  That the glass was located in a area covering Tall el-Hammam suggests to me a 
volcanic cinder bomb not cooling correctly as it comes down resulting in a superheated explosion on a limited scale.
</para>
<section>
<title>1628 BC: Destrection of Sodom and Gomorrah
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1628 BC: Ogygian Deluge
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1628 BC: The 10 Plagues of Egypt
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>10 Plagues</secondary></indexpara>
<indexpara><primary>10 Plagues</primary></indexpara>
</title>
<para>Plague 1 - Water turned into blood, fish died</para>
<para>
The redness in the Nile was caused by volcanic ash from Thera which is found in the Nile region. The silt would have make the Nile turn blood red, and would also render it undrinkable. Heavy rains in the red-soiled area of Lake Victoria could have caused reddened water to wash downstream.
</para>
<para>Plague 2 - Frogs</para>
<para>
Any blight on the water that killed fish also would have caused frogs to leave the river and probably die.
</para>
<para>Plagues 3 and 4 - Biting insects and flies</para>
<para>
The lack of frogs in the river would have let insect populations, normally kept in check by the frogs, increase massively.
</para>
<para>Plagues 5 and 6 - Livestock disease and boils</para>
<para>
There are biting flies in the region which transmit livestock diseases; a sudden increase in their number could spark epidemics.
</para>
<para>Plague 7 - Fiery hail</para>
<para>
Volcanic activity not only brings with it ash, but brimstone, and also alters the weather system, occasionally producing hail. Hail could also have occurred as a completely independent natural weather event, with accompanying lightning as the 'fire'.
</para>
<para>Plague 8 - Locusts</para>
<para>
The weight of hail will destroy most crops, leaving several insects and other animals without a normal food source. The remaining crops therefore would become targeted heavily, and thus be destroyed by swarms of locusts which would otherwise be distributed rather thinly. Or the locusts could have increased because of a lack of predators. Even without these explanations, swarms of locusts are not uncommon today.
</para>
<para>Plague 9 - Darkness</para>
<para>
There could be several causes for unusual darkness: a solar eclipse, a sandstorm, volcanic ash, or simply swarms of locusts large enough to block out the sun.
</para>
<para>Plague 10 - Death of the firstborn</para>
<para>
If the last plague indeed selectively tended to affect the firstborn, it could be due to food polluted during the time of darkness, either by locusts or by the black mold Cladosporium. When people emerged after the darkness, the firstborn would be given priority, as was usual, and would consequently be more likely to be affected by any toxin or disease carried by the food. Meanwhile, the Israelites ate food prepared and eaten very quickly which would have made it less likely to be infected.
</para><para>
In the 2006 documentary Exodus Decoded, Jewish Canadian filmmaker Simcha Jacobovici hypothesized the selectiveness of the tenth plague was under the circumstances similar to the 1986 disaster of Lake Nyos that is related to geological activities that caused the previous plagues in a related chain of events. The hypothesis was that the plagues took place shortly after the eruption of Thera (now known as Santorini), which happened some time between 1550 BC and 1650 BC, and recently narrowed to between 1627 BC - 1600 BC, with a 95% probability of accuracy. Jacobovici however places the eruption in 1500 BC. According to the documentary, the eruption sets off a chain of events resulting in the plagues and eventually the killing of the first born. Jacobovici suggests that the first born in ancient Egypt had the privilege to sleep close to the floor while other children slept on higher ground or even on roofs. This view, however, is not supported by any archaeological or historical evidence. As in Lake Nyos, when carbon dioxide or other toxic gases escape the surface tension of a nearby water body because of either geological activity or over-saturation, the gas, being heavier than air, 'flooded' the nearby area displacing oxygen and killing those who were in its path. Jewish households escaped the fate because they were told to observe their first Passover rituals.
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>Exodus
</title>
<para>
Research has shown that there were possibly two Exodus episodes.  The first due to the plagues of Egypt during the Santorini explosion and the 
section during the expltion of the Hyksos.
</para>
<section>
<title>1446 BC - 1350 BC: Exodus - First
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Exodus, First</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1300 BC - 1200 BC: Exodus - Second
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Exodus, Second</secondary></indexpara>
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1391 BC - 1271 BC: Moses
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Exodus, Second</secondary></indexpara>
<indexpara><primary>Biblical Event</primary><secondary>Moses</secondary></indexpara>
<indexpara><primary>Moses</primary></indexpara>
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1400 BC: Leviticus 19:19
</title>
<para>
' [the Hebrew people] shalt not sow their field with mingled seed... '(King James Bible)
</para>
<para>
Some scholars believe the phrase mingled seeds includes grafting, although this interpretation remains contentious among scholars.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>1500 BC: Tsunami at Tartessos area
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1500 BC - 1400 BC: Kaali Meteor Impact
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1460 BC: Taupo, New Zealand VEI 6
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1600 BC - 1500 BC: Joshua 6:17 - Destruction of Jerico
</title>
<para>The 'Battle' of Jerico and it subsiquent destruction of all living souls is a curious event in the history of Mosis and the tribes.
The elaborate clensing ritual for the aftermath of the battle seems to be more of a contamination clense than calming the soul so as 
to not murder your wife and children after killing everyone in Jerico.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>1500 BC: Small reoccupation of Jerico
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>1400 BC - 900 BC: Jerico unoccupied
</title>
</section>
</section>
</chapter>
