<chapter id='global_winter'>
<title>Global Winter<indexterm><primary>Global Winter</primary></indexterm></title>
<partition>Of things that go boom</partition>
<para>A global winter is a condition that was first examined in relation to Nuclear war.  What would happen if the globe suffered a winter condition that lasted several years?
While we hope that Nuclear war is not something that will affect history anytime soon, a volcano can and often does produce the effect.
Additionally, the impact of a comet or meteorite sufficiently large would also impact weather.
</para><para>
A global winter must be distinguished from a hemispheric winter which  affects only the middle to upper latitudes above or below the equator.
In 2009, a volcano in Iceland exploded and in the winter of 2010, Western Europe is suffering a severely cold winter.
While today, it is great  inconvenience to the inhabitants of Western Europe, in the past it would have meant the deaths of young and old from exposure and starvation.
When the cold extends into summer, a 'Winter' is happening.
</para><para>
In 1815, the Tambora volcano exploded resulting in a global winter within 'recorded' history.<footnote><para><emphasis>Volcano Weather: the story of 1816, the year without a summer</emphasis></para></footnote>
Indeed the records available demonstrate the extent to which the weather in North Eastern America changed is very dramatic.
When examined along side the records from Krakatoa, it can be seen that 1815 'winter' effect was significantly larger.
1815 is called the last crisis of subsistence where the ability of people to feed themselves was greatly challenged.</para>
<section>
<title>Definition</title>
<para>A Global winter is a climate event which encompasses the whole planet<footnote><para><emphasis>Volcanic Dry Fogs, Climate Cooling, and Plague Pandemics in Europe and the Middle East</emphasis></para></footnote>.
A cooling of the planet's temperature which affects plant growth significantly enough to affect food production.
Visions of Nuclear Winter have prevailed in the West since the inception of the Atomic bomb.
Yet, nature has provided us with an example of what we need fear.
Until the age of modern transportation and specifically the train, famine would be the result during the cold years due to bare subsistence living of most of the people.
</para><para>
The 'Winter' follows a pattern of a couple of years of cold followed by a couple of years of relatively normal weather.
Then an additional couple of years of cold.
After this, the weather would begin to dampen back to the normal patterns established by the ocean circulation.
</para><para>
This sequence is usually 5 to 7 years longs and consists of the following:
<ol>
<li>
The event phase is when the ejaculate is in the air.
The cooling is primarily reflection of heat back into space.
The length of this event depends on the volume of ejaculate and the amount of SO2 released.
It can last from one to two years.
The first winter after the event can be the coldest as the cooled waters in the loop combine with the cooling events of the event cloud to produce lower temperatures depending on what month the event occures.
This influence consists of two things, the first is the amount of exposure of water in the north Atlantic loop as well as the amount of air heat trapped under the ash cloud.
Events in the first part of the year do not have the time to accumulate the heat necessary for a normal climate.
Events in the later half of the year have the accumulated heat in the loop to moderate the first winter.
</li>
<li>
The pipeline phase is when the warm waters reach Europe after the settling out of the ejaculate in the air.
The conditions would be cool air with warm ocean currents.
This seems to be about two years in length.
</li>
<li>
The event pipeline phase consists of the cooled waters in the Thermohaline circulation which were cooled during the time that the ejaculate was in the atmosphere.  This lasts about the length that the ejaculate was in air as well as the effects of the SO2 released.
</li>
</ol>
</para><para>
The difference between a global  and a hemispheric winter is that the hemispheric winter is usually a couple of years of cold followed by fairly normal weather.  In the northern hemisphere, the weather would be a cold atmosphere with a warm ocean current.
Not much effect would be felt about four years down the line when waters warmed in the Pacific tootles along side Europe as most of those waters are warmed in the southern pacific.
</para><para>
A event in the Southern Hemisphere would have an immediate effect on Australia and South America and southern Africa as well as an effect on Europe as soon as two years latter since all the waters on the way to Europe are coursing through the southern hemisphere and would last longer than a purely northern event as the main volume of water in the Thermohaline circulation runs through the southern hemisphere.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Famine</title>
<para>Famine<indexterm><primary>Famine</primary></indexterm> was very common event with an extreme change of weather.
The Year without a Summer in 1816 was the last great Crisis of subsistence in the Western Hemisphere.
After that year, modern transportation has eased the burdens of feeding the population.
</para><para>
In ancient time, an extreme weather event would result in famine with in a year.
If the event occur ed early in the year and no real crops where harvested, famine would occur.
With a truncated harvest, famine would start early the next year.
From a simple event, there could be 1 to 2 years of no or substandard harvests followed by 2 years of barely sufficient harvests followed by another 2 to 3 years of substandard harvests.</para>
<section>
<title>1315 AD - 1317 AD: The Great Famine
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>535 AD - 544 AD: Year of Darkness - global winter
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>535 AD: Failure of Bread
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>539 AD: Failure of Bread
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>540 AD: Failure of Bread
</title>
</section>
<section>
<title>304 AD - 306 AD: Famines and Epidemics</title>
<para>Empire wide Stathakopoulos states that the statement that the living were outnumbered by the dead is topoi as far as records go, but many have a basis in fact.
Consider that the Plague of Cyprian was smallpox and when introduced to new areas would have a potential decimating effect.</para>
<event_type>Epidemic</event_type>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>Plagues: A history of plagues, a plague of histories
<indexterm><primary>Epidemic</primary><secondary>Smallpox</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Smallpox</primary></indexterm>
</title>
<para>A common pattern to extreme weather events is plague.
Plague is different from an epidemic in that diseases like smallpox, measles and mumps were introduced and stayed in the populations of Europe and the Middle east eventually becoming childhood diseases in the cases of mumps and measles.
</para><para>
The plagues of Antonine<footnote><para>165 - 189 AD</para></footnote>  and Cyprian<footnote><para>251 - 270 AD</para></footnote> were the result of the introduction of Smallpox into the Roman army on the borders of the empire resulting in the spread of the disease into the heart land of Rome.
It is believed that both of these epidemic were Smallpox because tests on the measles virus lead some to believe that it did not evolve into it present form until around 1,000 AD<footnote><para>Wiki reference</para></footnote>.
</para><para>
Global Winter events always have some sort of epidemic factors involved be it typhoid fever via local rodent population explosion/collapse or the plague from the same explosion/collapse on the plague caring rodents in Africa.
If the 'Winter' is severe enough, plague rears out of Africa traveling along the eastern coast to the Red sea and it connection to the Mediterranean<footnote><para>Justinian's Flea</para></footnote>.
</para><para>
During the Little Ice Age (1300-1850), the Black  Death was not the only plague to hit Europe<footnote><para>Rats, Lice and History</para></footnote>.
</para><para>
Typhus made an appearance as the Plague of Athens becoming the second appearance in recorded Greek history.
The fist is argued as the appearance of disease in the openings of the Iliad which ravages for 9 days destroying horses, mules, dogs and finally humans.
Sent by Apollo via his 'army' of mice<footnote><para>Iliad</para></footnote>.
</para><para>
Bubonic plague's effects on animals other than rats and man is complex.
Cats are very susceptible to the plague and as hunters of rats would be the first animals affects when a rat die off occurs.
Dogs are not affected by the plague, but can carry the plague fleas until they die of malnutrition and dehydration.
Black footed ferrets can also carry the plague fleas without harm<footnote><para>Yellow fever, black goddess</para></footnote>.
</para>
<section>
<title>1150 BC: Trojan War</title>
<para>Apollo his association with mice and their caring of plague was noted in the Iliad.
That such an association should be stated so clearly indicated a long standing understanding of causes of disease.
</para>
<event_type>Epidemic</event_type>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>430 BC: Plague of Athens</title>
<para>Typhoid appears amount the Athenians.</para>
<event_type>Epidemic</event_type>
</section>
<section>
<title>165 - 180 AD: Antonine Plague - First appearance of Smallpox</title>
<para>The plague decimated the army with a 13 to 15 percent loss with the cities suffering similarly while the rural population suffered 7 to 10 percent in loss of life.
When the Roman army contracted due to the plague, the Mauri invaded conquering the Rio Tinto area leading to the loss of the silver supplying the army.
</para><para>
Striping the value from the coin lead to economic unrest resulting in the Crisis of the Third Century.</para>
<event_type>Epidemic</event_type>
</section>
<section>
<title>251 - 270 AD: Plague of Cyprian - Second appearance of Smallpox</title>
<para>This plague is credited with having a substantial amount of influence of public view of Christianity as only the Christians were attending the plague victims.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bubonic Plague
<indexterm><primary>Epidemic</primary><secondary>Bubonic Plague</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>Bubonic Plague</primary></indexterm>
</title>
<event_type>Epidemic</event_type>
<para>The first occurrence of plague in Europe was about 1500 BC.
This first epidemic did not reach Britain.
The second plague was 541 and then the third in 1347.
The reason that I say not Britain in the first plague is that in the second, the Celtic portion of Britain (the Anglo-Saxons had the other half) the effect was a decimation of the population.
The Waste Lands of Arthur legions started here with area totally emptied of population and others reflecting the shrunken survivors.
</para><para>
Anglo-Saxon Britons did not suffer the same extent of population damage when the plague finally hit them in the 560's.
When the Black Death hit England, the death toll was similar to that suffered by Constantinople in 541, about half.
</para><para>
While the first two occurrences of plague came to Europe via climate change, the third visit was due to that other great determiner of cultural change - War.</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>1500 BC: First Occurrence of the Plague</title>
<para>Plague strikes Egypt.</para>
<event_type>Epidemic</event_type>
</section>
<section>
<title>541 AD: Justian Plague.  Second Occurrence</title>
<para>An Empire is not only the ground help by those disposed to its existence, but also the people.
Its citizens who serve as government, religious, cultural and business leaders from ties between communities that are based on trust and mutual understanding.  When plague strikes, the indiscriminate manner of death leads to an uneven distribution of contacts over the larger state.
</para><para>
With such a reduction in communal contentedness, the concept of greater nationhood ceases to exist.
The trust and mutual understanding coming from known personal constants reduces to knowledge of a brother's cousin's friend's cousin.
Family to Family contacts exist if the Family exists.
After a plague, a family's reduction in size reduces it knowledge of the business and its properties.
</para><para>
The Manorialism started in the Third century contributed to this reduction in knowledge because instead of masters of a craft spread out amount the population, they were isolated in number to a Manor.
The lost of an estates master with the job following to a journeyman would cause the Estate owner to seek out a master of the craft if they could be found.</para>
<event_type>Epidemic</event_type>
<section>
<title>1347 AD - 1351 AD: Black Death - The third occurance of Plague in Europe
</title>
<event_type>Epidemic</event_type>
</section>
</section>
<section>
<title>Plague vs. Famine</title>
<para>The after effects of Plagues and Famines differ in who dies during such an event.
During Famines, it is the young, the old, the sick, the poor.
People with skills are cared for by the community and its lord.   At least successful cultures provided for the skilled during famine.
</para><para>
In terms of cultural disasters, a plague is the worst save war.
Plague are non-discriminatory in the selection of victims.
Rich, poor, healthy, sick - all are likely to be struck.
A plague does not differentiate between classes, anyone exposed become a potently victim.
This consequent of plague is called 'The loss of cultural complexity'.
</para><para>
A typical shop would consist of the owner/master craftsman, a journeyman and a few apprentices.
During a famine, the apprentices may have to fend for themselves.
During a plague, one of the apprentices may be the only person left after the epidemic is over.
How then does the business recover?
With the master, he can start over with new apprentices until they are journeymen themselves.
The journeyman can take over with a loss of complexity of what is possible for the business.
The master held all the keys, the journeyman most.
An apprentice may be able with talent, skill and determination rebuild a business in the event on the only surviving practitioner of that occupation.
An intelligent person would be able to work backwards from examples of existing items to recreate their appearance, but not the real item.
The type of glassed used in pottery, the technique used to temper iron for a certain use, the herbal mixture which helps with joint pain are examples lost when a plague strikes.
</para><para>
Imagine you are setting at a dinner table at a conference.
To think of a famine, look at the people around you and think that 1 or 2 people were not there.
This is a famine in it first couple of years.
If a couple of more people are missing then, a longer famine is ensuring.
Now image that the person on either side of you is gone.
A plague which removes half the population.
Look on at every other person at the table.
Now think that you are only person at the table and that you have to look at other tables for company.
This is a plague where 90% die.
Culture does not survive because the simple act of survival does not allow for complex anything.
</para><para>
In the first year, grandma dies; the youngest child.
In the second year, the middle child; perhaps an aunt.
In the third year, we recover.  In the fourth year, we have another child.
In the fifth year, the child dies from starvation; another middle child; perhaps  an uncle.
Finally, the eldest child is endangered.
What parent would not do what they must to ensure survival of their eldest child?</para>
</section>
</chapter>
