<chapter id='introduction'>
<title>Introduction
</title>
<partition>Introduction</partition>
<para>My first and primary occupation in life has been Computer Science.  From beginning with Basic on a Woods<footnote><para>Pencil and paper</para></footnote> computer and the December 1973 Popular Science magazine's article on the Intel 8080 microprocessor chip to today's cloud environment, Computer Science and its practice has allowed me to sharpen my skills at pattern recognition.  
</para>
<para>
The science of Computer Science is finding the patterns that define the interaction and manipulation of data and doing so in an efficient manner.  The engineering art of Computer Science is in finding ways to apply those patterns to an ever changing array of data and the needs for knowledge that arises from the crunching of that data.
</para>
<para>
This pattern awareness lead me to Chinese Medicine and a degree and license in Chinese Medicine and Acupuncture.    The Chinese over the course of millennium have discovered patterns in how the body reacts to bacteriological and viral influences as well as metabolic changes.
Their effect lead to a model of what a healthy person should be as they age.  
As time passed the Chinese scholars augmented the understanding of these traditions with descriptions of patterns related to epidemics and chronic health problems endemic to Mankind.  
</para>
<para>
Chinese Medicine
<indexterm><primary>Chinese medicine</primary></indexterm>
 lead me to study the epidemics of history looking at the patterns that a virus would have on society.  In 220 AD Zhong Zhung Zhing 
published the 'Shan Han Lun' (The treatment of Cold Disorders).   
This book came about because Dr Zhong lost three quarters of his clan to an epidemic (believed to be Typhus)
causing him to begin the practice of medicine to aid the survivors. 
85% of the herbal formulas in this book are still in use today.
</para>
<para>
Having looked at the history of several epidemics, it is apparent to me that many people cannot comprehend the horror of the mass destruction of humanity and as a result reduce the observations of past historians with remarks of 'of course, that cannot be correct'  in reference to figures stated by various people in their writings.
Yet, time has proved many historians of the past to be accurate to the extent of their observations and it is not incomprehensible that in fact at various place during the Justian Plague and the Black Death that populations in some areas were indeed decimated with 9 of 10 people dying just as other places felt no losses.
</para>
<para>
Documentation of this phenomena are in the modern worlds interactions with 'lost' tribes in the Amazon and how first contact results in a 90% loss of life.
Cortez conquered Mexico due to Smallpox and other viruses that the Incas had caught from Cortez and his crew.   
</para>
<para>
In the Amazon, there are archaeological digs going on documenting the settlements abandoned 500 years ago<footnote><para>Amazon archaeology of 1500 settlements</para></footnote>.   
With the destruction of a civilization to such an extent, more than culture is lost as the skills to continue basic survival are reduced to subsistence level at best.  
Plague is indiscriminate in its effects on the knowledge level of a population.  
During a famine,
<indexterm><primary>Famine</primary></indexterm>
 it is the young, the sick, the old, the weak who die first.  
People with skills survive because people reliant on those skills will support those individuals possessing them.   
The concept of the 'noblar third'.  During a plague, the loss of this third results in the degredation of civilization.
During a plague, your chances are dependent on exposure, genes and preexisting immune system strength which paradoxically does not ensure the survival of the fittest.  
During the 'Swine' flu epidemic of 1919, it was the young and strong that died is most numbers.  
Their immune systems launched too strong of an attack resulting in an autoimmune condition.  
During the 2008 round of Swine flu, it was children who were most effected with prolonged effects observed.  
<footnote><para>I remember that during the Swine flu the early 1970's, my father was struck with flu and pneumonia.</para></footnote></para>
<para>
This pattern of epidemics on a native<footnote><para>Exposure of 'lost' tribes to diseases</para></footnote> population can possibly be used to explain the mystery of the Minion's disappearance from history as well as the interesting fact that an epidemic of 1,500BC left its mark on the gene pool of Europe<footnote><para>Gene study which lead to discovery of European plague in 1500BC</para></footnote>.
</para>
<para>
Modern sanitation tends to belay the effects of disease on a naive population.  
Even the comparatively recent impact of European diseases on American Indians is reduced to the 'Moral' principle with the idea being that those who are not affected by a disease have higher morals than those affected.  
This is similar to the 'Barbarian Virtues' theory of behavior in parts of the modern world.  
If we practice 'Barbarian Virtues' (rape, pillage and murder) we will be praised and rewarded by God as those are the Virtues that God has rewarded in the past.  
</para>
<para>
These acts of God as plagues have been labeled in the past have often appeared at times of extreme upheaval in human affairs.  
This begs the chicken-egg question of are the upheavals at such times a result of the plague, a cause of the plague or are both caused by some third set of circumstances.  
</para><para>
The premises of this book is that there are types of events which can lead to both the conditions for societal upheaval as well as account for an explosion of plague causing agents.  
These events are caused by extreme weather due to volcanic events or the impact of a comet or meteor.  
Each type of event has its own effects yet all have a similar effect on weather and short term climate changes.
</para>
<para>
This effect is to create a Global or Hemispheric Winter. 
 
A condition under which the temperature is low and plants do not grow due to cold and low light conditions.  
In the 535-6 event, the effect was described as a year of living in eclipse as that was the resulting light density from the sun filtering through the dust throw up into the atmosphere. During the 'Cold War', much discussion was given to the effects of a Nuclear Winter.  A similar condition, but with nuclear radiation to contend with as well.  
</para>
</chapter>
